A Finding Aid to the Ad Reinhardt Papers, 1927-1968, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ad Reinhardt papers
1927-1968
Archives of American Art
Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967
AAA.reinad
Archival Resource Key
3.9 Linear feet
The papers of Ad Reinhardt measure 3.9 linear feet and date from circa 1927 to 1968. The collection documents Reinhardt's career as an abstract painter, cartoonist, and writer through biographical material, correspondence, writings, printed material, scrapbooks, and artwork.
Biographical Note
Ad Reinhardt was born "Frederick Adolph Reinhardt" in 1913 in Buffalo, New York. He would, by the time he enrolled in elementary school, go by the name of Adolph Friedrich Reinhardt, which he would use on official documents for the rest of his life. Shortly after he was born, his family moved to Queens, New York. As a child he copied "funnies" and made collages from newspapers and won many school and community prizes for his artwork. In the fall of 1931 he entered Columbia University and studied art history under Meyer Schapiro, who encouraged him to get involved in radical campus politics. Reinhardt became the editor and cover designer of Jester, a campus magazine. After graduating in 1935, he trained as a painter at the National Academy of Design under Karl Anderson, and at the American Artists School under Francis Criss and Carl Holty, until 1937. At this time he joined American Abstract Artists and became affiliated with American artistic-political groups and other artist organizations. From 1936 to 1941 he worked for the Works Progress Administration (WPA) Federal Art Project, Easel Division, while simultaneously developing his mature style of linear, abstract painting.
When his work for the Federal Art Project ended, Reinhardt worked as a commercial and freelance writer and graphic artist for pamphlets and magazines. Most notably, he was a reporter and cartoonist for the newspaper PM from 1942 to 1947. After serving in the Navy from 1946 to 1947, he took a position as an art history professor at Brooklyn College where he taught for twenty years. During his career as a professor he was also a visiting lecturer at several universities, including Yale University from 1952 to 1953, and the California School of Fine Arts in 1950. Reinhardt had a keen interest in Asiatic art and would often lecture and write on this subject. In the late 1950s and early 1960s he traveled to Japan, India, Persia, Egypt, Turkey, Syria, and Jordan.
Reinhardt began exhibiting his paintings early in his career. In 1946 he joined the Betty Parsons Gallery, which also represented many other prominent Abstract Expressionists, including Mark Rothko, Barnet Newman, and Jackson Pollock. Reinhardt rejected the emotionalism found in Abstract Expressionism and sought to produce geometric, minimalist paintings. In developing his own aesthetic theory, he wrote extensively for art periodicals such as Art News and Art International. His artwork culminated in the 1960s with his series of black paintings, which drew much attention from the art community and the public. A major retrospective of his work was held at the Jewish Museum in New York, NY, in 1960. Reinhardt continued to write and work on his series of black paintings until his death in 1967.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ad Reinhardt measure 3.9 linear feet and date from 1927 to 1968. The collection documents Reinhardt's career as an abstract painter, cartoonist, and writer through biographical material, correspondence, writings, printed material, scrapbooks, and artwork.
Biographical material includes personal and professional records, such as passports and membership cards as well as an artist's chronology, and material documenting Reinhardt's time at Brooklyn College and his work for the WPA. Correspondence is of a general nature, including letters from art galleries, museums, and art dealers about exhibitions and artwork, colleges and universities concerning lectures and workshops, and letters from friends, art critics, and fellow artists, including Lucy Lippard, Abe Ajay, and George Rickey. Also found are letters from magazines and various art and social organizations. Writings and notes include calendars, and a small amount of notes and draft writings by Reinhardt. Printed material comprises the largest series in the collection and contains exhibition materials, including invitations and catalogs, and a large number of magazine and news clippings, primarily about Reinhardt's career and modern art, but also covering other topics of interest to him, such as Asian art. Also found in this series are clippings of his published cartoons and artwork. Scrapbooks contain additional printed material documenting his high school and college days, as well as his career. as an artist. Also found within the papers is a small amount of artwork by Reinhardt, primarily small sketches.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 6 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1928-1967 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1930-1967 (Boxes 1-2; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1953-1966 (Box 2; 7 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1927-1968 (Boxes 2-4; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 5: Scrapbooks, circa 1928-1959 (Boxes 4-5; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1946, 1950, 1961 (Box 4; 4 folders)
Related Material
Related collections found in the Archives includes Ad Reinhardt postcards (to Katherine Scrivener), Ad Reinhardt letters and artwork (loaned material, available on microfilm only), Abe Ajay correspondence with Ad Reinhardt, Marjorie Grimm printed material and letters received from Ad Reinhardt, one photograph of Ad Reinhardt and Colette Roberts by William R. Simmons, and a 1955 painting by Ad Reinhardt.
Separated Material
The Archives of American Art also holds material lent for microfilming (reels N69-99 - N69-103) including additional notes, writings, correspondence, photographs of artwork, and travel logs. Lent materials were returned to the lender and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Provenance
Rita Reinhardt, Ad Reinhardt's widow, donated papers and lent material for micorfilming in 1969.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
This site provides access to the papers of Ad Reinhardt in the Archives of American Art that were digitized in 2010, and total 5160 images.
Documents containing sensitive personal information and clippings and documents unrelated to Ad Reinhardt have not been scanned.
Materials lent for microfilming are available on 35mm microfilm reels N69-99- N69-103 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Works of art; Scrapbooks; Art, Modern; Cartoonists -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Brooklyn College -- Faculty; United States. Works Progress Administration
- Biographical Material, circa 1928-1967; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material documents Reinhardt's personal life, as well as his career and his participation in the art community. This series contains several drafts of an artist's chronology written by Reinhardt that places his life and career in the context of the larger modern art movement and illuminates many important moments in his life. Also included are numerous identification documents, such as his passports, membership cards to various art, political, and social organizations, and a fellowship application form containing an artist statement and other biographical information. Also found are materials documenting Reinhardt's service in the military, his work for the WPA, and his professorship at Brooklyn College. This series contains Reinhardt's high school yearbook, business cards and event ephemera collected by him, his address book and lists, as well as exhibition labels from exhibits at Betty Parsons Gallery and the Jewish Museum.
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged alphabetically and items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  This series has been partially scanned.
  Items not scanned include those containing sensitive personal information.
  - Address Books and Lists, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artist's Chronology, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blood Donor Registration Book, 1939, 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brooklyn College Faculty Forms, 1957, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Business Cards, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Credit Cards, 1963-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Event Ephemera, 1963, 1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Labels, circa 1956-1960, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fellowship Application Form, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Identification Cards, 1940, circa 1952-1953, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Material on Frank and Olga Reinhardt, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Membership Cards, 1936-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newton High School Yearbook, 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - New York University Bursar's Receipts, 1946-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Passports, 1952, 1958, 1961, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Selective Service Documentation, 1941-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - United States Navy Records, 1940-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Veterans Administration Documentation, 1945-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Works Progress Administration Documentation, 1940-1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, 1928-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, circa 1930-1967; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 1-2; 1.1 linear feet)
  This series contains correspondence documenting Reinhardt's career as an artist and art professor, with the bulk of the material dating from 1946 to 1966. Most of the letters are incoming, and there are only a few draft copies of outgoing letters written by Reinhardt. Found in this series are several letters from artists, including Abe Ajay, cartoonist Dave Crockett Johnson, Helen Frankenthaler, George Rickey, and May Wilson, as well as letters from art critics and writers, including Lucy Lippard, and Ned O'Gorman. Reinhardt also received a large number of letters from art galleries and art dealers, including Betty Parsons Gallery, Iris Clert, Dwan Gallery, and Jock Truman, and art museums, including the Museum of Modern Art, Jewish Museum, and the Whitney Museum of American Art, regarding the exhibition, loan, or sale of his artwork. Numerous letters in this series concern his participation as a guest lecturer, visiting artist, or symposium participant at colleges and universities throughout the country, as well as his professorship at Brooklyn College.
  Reinhardt was a member of many art, political, and social organizations and his involvement is documented here in letters from groups such as the Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation, and the Foundation for the Arts, Religion, and Culture. Also included are letters from magazines and other publications to which he contributed articles and artwork, including PM newspaper and Artforum. There is also a large amount of fan mail sent to PM and to Reinhardt in praise of his series of drawings of the history of modern art for that newspaper. Miscellaneous folders include letters of the same type mentioned above which only consist of one or two letters from a correspondent. Notable correspondents within the miscellaneous folders include Josef Albers, John Ashbery, John Cage, Columbia Pictures Corporation, Mathias Goeritz, Peggy Guggenheim, Jasper Johns, Donald Judd, Ray Johnson, Ellsworth Kelly, Robert Kennedy, Robert Motherwell, Claes Oldenburg, Barbara Rose, Meyer Schapiro, and Russel Wright.
  Letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  This series has been scanned been in its entirety.
  - A, Miscellaneous, 1946-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ajay, Abe, 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1957-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Institute of Architects, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Architectural League of New York, 1956-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Art Association of Indianapolis, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Artforum, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Arts Fraud Investigation, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - B, Miscellaneous, 1943-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation, 1963-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Betty Parsons Gallery, 1961-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Brooklyn College, 1946-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bucknell University, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - C, Miscellaneous: Ca-Ch, 1946-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - C, Miscellaneous: Ci-Cu, 1930-1967, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Carpenter, Charles, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Clert, Iris, 1960-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Columbia University Teachers College, 1934, 1944-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), 1963-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Cooper Union, 1955-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Crockett Johnson, Dave, 1961-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - D-E, Miscellaneous, 1946-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Dayton Art Institute, 1959-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Dissent Magazine, 1963-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Dlugoszewski, Lucia, 1963-1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Dwan Gallery, 1962-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 1935-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Fan Mail, undated; 1946 February-April; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Fan Mail, 1946 May-June; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Fan Mail, 1946 July-October; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Fan Mail, 1946 November-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Finlay, Ian Hamilton, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Fitzsimmons, James, 1962-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Foundation for the Arts, Religion, and Culture, 1962-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Frankenthaler, Helen, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1944-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - George Braziller, Inc., 1962-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Graham Modern Painting and Sculpture, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Guggenheim Museum, 1961-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 1940-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Hess, Thomas, 1954-circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Hewitt, Frank, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Hunter, Sam (Rose Art Museum), 1963, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - I-J, Miscellaneous, 1945-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Institute of Contemporary Arts, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Jewish Museum, 1962-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1946-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1943-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Lippard, Lucy, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Longview Foundation, Inc., 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - M, Miscellaneous: Ma-Me, 1947-1956, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - M, Miscellaneous: Mi-Mu, 1948-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Maryland Institute College of Art, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Museum Boymans-van Beuningen, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1952-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - N, Miscellaneous, 1940-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - National Council of Women of the United States, Inc., 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - New Jersey Water Color Society, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - O-P, Miscellaneous, 1943-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - O'Gorman, Ned, circa 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ohio State University, 1959-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - PM Newspaper, 1946-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Powers, Marcella, 1946-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Q-R, Miscellaneous, 1957-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rickey, George, 1963-1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - S, Miscellaneous, 1943-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - School Art League of New York City, 1948-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Southern Illinois University, 1961-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Syracuse University, 1957, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - T, Miscellaneous, 1942-1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Truman, Jock, 1964-1965, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - U, Miscellaneous, 1939-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, 1956-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - University of Oregon, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - V, Miscellaneous, 1956-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Village Art Center, 1949-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - W, Miscellaneous, 1938-1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1963-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Waggaman, John F., circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Washington Gallery of Modern Art, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1953-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Wilson, May, 1961-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Y-Z, Miscellaneous, 1943-1947, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Yale University, 1952-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Unidentified letters, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Unidentified letters, 1944-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1953-1966; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; (Box 2; 7 folders)
  Scattered writings include annotated calendars compiled by Reinhardt, drafts of published writings, such as the essay "Who is Responsible for Ugliness," drafts of letters, and other notes and lists on topics including modern art, aesthetics, and his career as an artist. Also found are lists of Chinese words and phrases written by Reinhardt during his study of Chinese art, a small number of photocopies from microfilm of other writings on art, and select pages from Reinhardt's notebooks. The only item in this series that wasn't written by Reinhardt is a progress report submitted to Reinhardt by a student in one of his classes.
  Researchers should note that many of Reinhardt's notebooks and other extensive writings were loaned for microfilming and returned to the donor and are only available on reels N69-99 and N69-103. These writings are not listed in this finding aid.
  Items are arranged by type of material and chronologically within each folder.
  This series has been partially scanned. Items not scanned include those that are prints of the microfilm.
  - Calendars, 1958-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Calendars, 1963; 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Chinese Words and Phrases, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Draft Writings and Notes, 1953, 1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Pages from Notebooks (Photocopies), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Progress Report from Student, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Writings about Art (Photocopies), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Printed Material, circa 1927-1968; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; (Boxes 2-4; 1.7 linear feet)
  This series contains published material that Reinhardt collected to document his career as an artist and his research on various topics. Included are numerous newspaper and magazine clippings of articles about his artwork and modern art in general, including articles written by Reinhardt. Also found are clippings that Reinhardt collected on other topics such as Asian art, architecture, Christian art, and aesthetics, and book reviews on many of these topics. Many of these clippings are annotated by Reinhardt with handwritten comments and underlined segments. Also in this series are announcements, invitations, catalogs, and posters for exhibitions of Reinhardt's art and the artwork of others, as well as other event announcements, calendars, and press releases for lectures, workshops, and benefits. Other items found here are brochures, conference programs, journals and newsletters from organizations, publications from his time as a student, and examples of his published artwork, including covers of Listen magazine and clippings of his numerous published cartoons.
  This series has been partially scanned. Items not scanned include clippings and other items not related to Ad Reinhardt.
  - Book Reviews, 1962, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Brochures, 1940, 1959, 1966, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Scope and Contents
    Conserved item housed in OV 6
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, 1931-1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, 1947-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, 1952-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, 1956-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Clippings, Ad Reinhardt and Modern Art, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 53)